<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to a late pamphlet, called A Sober dialogue, between a Scotch Presbyterian a London church-man, and a real Quaker, scandalously reflecting on the Church of England as if her doctrine and common-prayer did justifie the antichristian doctrine, of the real Quaker, viz. that the light within, whither in heathen, or Christian is sufficient to salvation without anything else; wherein the plain deism and antichristian principles of the real Quaker and his party, and the pretended church man, are plainly detected. By a friend to the author of the dialogue, called, a Sober dialogue, between a country friend, a London friend, and one of G.K.'s friends.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25515</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3305A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214848</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826904</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826904</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31315</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25515)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31315)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1901:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to a late pamphlet, called A Sober dialogue, between a Scotch Presbyterian a London church-man, and a real Quaker, scandalously reflecting on the Church of England as if her doctrine and common-prayer did justifie the antichristian doctrine, of the real Quaker, viz. that the light within, whither in heathen, or Christian is sufficient to salvation without anything else; wherein the plain deism and antichristian principles of the real Quaker and his party, and the pretended church man, are plainly detected. By a friend to the author of the dialogue, called, a Sober dialogue, between a country friend, a London friend, and one of G.K.'s friends.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Sam. Clark in George-yard in Lombard-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698/9 [i.e. 1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: A sober dialogue.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sober dialogue --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31315:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31315:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER To a Late PAMPHLET, Called a <hi>Sober Dialogue,</hi> Between a <hi>Scotch Presbyterian</hi> a <hi>London Church-man,</hi> and a <hi>Real Quaker,</hi> ſcandalouſly reflecting on the <hi>Church of England,</hi> As if her <hi>Doctrine and Common-Prayer</hi> did juſtifie the Antichriſtian Doctrine, of the Real Quaker, <hi>viz. That the Light Within, whither in Heathen, or Chriſtian is ſufficient to Salvation without any thing elſe;</hi> wherein the plain Deiſm and Anti-Chriſtian Principles of the Real Quaker and his Party, and the pretended Church-man, are plainly detected. By a Friend to the Author of the Dialogue, called, a <hi>Sober Dialogue,</hi> between a <hi>Country Friend,</hi> a <hi>London Friend,</hi> and one of <hi>G. K.</hi>'s <hi>Friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Sam. Clark</hi> in <hi>George-yard</hi> in <hi>Lombard-ſtreet.</hi> 1698/9.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:31315:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to a late Pamphlet, called, a <hi>Sober Dialogue,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>PAg. 4. The real Quaker is brought in, ſaying, <q rend="inline">I am of Opinion there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more excellent, than <hi>Light,</hi> or more laſting than <hi>Truth,</hi> and therefore the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt did well, when he Prayed to joyn them together, and the walking in one, and loving the other, as they ought to be, would put an end to all thoſe Notions, vain Conceptions, and Imaginations of Men, about which in their prejudiced Minds they trouble themſelves and the World?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That place of the Pſalmiſt, to which the real Quaker refers, is groſly Perverted by him, as is the uſual way of moſt of their Teachers to pervert the Scriptures through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and to diſcover the Perverſion, let the Words be conſidered as they are Written in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 43.3. <hi>O ſend out thy light and thy truth, let them lead me, let them bring me unto thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hill, and to thy tabernacle.</hi> Here it is evident to every intelligent Chriſtian, that the <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> that he Prayed for, was not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the <hi>Divine Word, or</hi> λογοσ, for he knew
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:31315:2"/>that was in all Men, and in all Creatures, it being one of his eſſential Attributes to be Omnipreſent. Nor, Secondly, The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Ilſumination of <hi>that Divine Word,</hi> as it was in all Men, to wit, Heathens and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels; for ſeeing the Quakers, ſay all Men, have that already; <hi>David</hi> had it alſo; but the <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> that he Prayed for, was ſome further Degree of ſpecial Illuminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Diſcovery of <hi>Divine Truth,</hi> which no Heathens and Infidels had.</p>
            <p>But if any Degree of <hi>Light</hi> that <hi>David</hi> had, was ſufficient without any thing elſe for his Salvation, why did he Pray for more, or why did he believe in Chriſt that was to come without him, to be a Sacrifice for our Sins, as all the Faithful did?</p>
            <p>Page the ſame, The ſuppoſed Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian is brought in, ſaying, he pitieth the Quakers Ignorance, [and ſo indeed he might very well do] for his affirming that by the <hi>Light Within,</hi> any can be ſaved <hi>without ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe,</hi> meaning by <hi>that ſomewhat elſe,</hi> with all true Chriſtians, the Godhead and Manhood of Chriſt, by the Perſonal Union of the two Natures, conſtituting one Chriſt Jeſus, who only as thus conſidered, is our intire and all-ſufficient Saviour; together with all the ſpiritual and ſpecial Bleſſings that the Faithful have by him, in the uſe of the ordinary outward Means of Salvation,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31315:3"/>as the Doctrin of the Holy Scriptures out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly Preached and Read, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> For this, <hi>the Church-man bids him hold, and not be too Cenſorious,</hi> as if it were the Doctrin of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that the <hi>Light within</hi> any Man, even (ſuppoſe) conſidered as the divine Word, doth ſave him, without being made Fleſh, that is to ſay, without his Manhood Perſonally Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his Godhead, which the leaſt Child in the Church of <hi>England</hi> that hath learned his Catechiſme, knoweth to be directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrin of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and all other Chriſtian Churches.</p>
            <p>Page 5. The Quaker ſaith, by the <hi>Light Within,</hi> he means no other than Chriſt, as the divine Word, or λογοσ, which enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens every Man that comes into the World, and for the Reſtoration of Man, God hath given unto every Man, and in, and by this <hi>Light,</hi> Invites, Calls, Exhorts, and ſtrives with every Man, in order to ſave them, which as it is received, and not reſiſted, works the Salvation of all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here he diſcovers plainly his deiſm, without any Diſguiſe, which is no wonder, ſeeing <hi>G. W.</hi> hath given him a Preſident, in his late <hi>Antidote,</hi> p. 28. Confeſſing that the Quakers are offended with <hi>G. K.</hi>'s Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, ſaying, that <hi>the Light within is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to Salvation, without ſomething elſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:31315:3"/>
            <p>And here this real Quaker gives us a plain Account, what his Chriſt is, to wit, the Divine λογοσ, or Word without Chriſt's Manhood, and all that he did and ſuffered for us without us, and all that he is now do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for us in Heaven. All which are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe than the <hi>Light Within,</hi> either Saint or Infidel, and wharever Uſe or Service the common Illumination hath in all Men, by way of ſome preparatory Miniſtration, yet to ſay it actually ſaveth, or that Chriſt actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſaveth any Man by it alone, without Chriſt's Manhood, and Sacrifice, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation in Heaven, is pure Heatheniſme, and Deiſme, and renders Chriſt's Dying to be in vain, and the Preaching and Faith of it unneceſſary to any.</p>
            <p>Page the ſame. The ſuppoſed Presbyterian ving ſaid, that in Men that reproves for Sin, is only the Law Written in the Heart, in p. 6. The Church-man is made to Check the Presbyterian, and to tell him, he ſears he does not well conſider this Word <hi>only;</hi> for if it be granted that it's Chriſt, as the di ine Word that reproves for Sin, as the Quakers ſay, then don't you carry it too far by Aſſerting it's only the Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The ſaying, that in Men that reproves for Sin is only the Law, hath this true obvious Senſe, without any ſtrain, to wit, the common Illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31315:4"/>that is in all Men, allowing it to be given by Chriſt, as a common Gift, as well as our Reaſons as Men, are the Gifts of God, and of the divine Word in common to all Mankind. And this Senſe the Quaker is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to hold to, if he will follow his great Patrons, <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> and <hi>W. Penn,</hi> who have Printed it more than once; that the Quakers do not affirm that Chriſt is in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man, but that a Light by or from Chriſt is in every Man. This the Presbyterian may well ſay, with the Holy Scriptures, and all ſound Chriſtians, that the Light in every Man, in the Senſe of <hi>G. W.</hi> and <hi>W. P.</hi> by the <hi>Light,</hi> not underſtanding Chriſt, but the <hi>Light</hi> or Illumination given from Chriſt to every Man, is only the Law Written in the Heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaker.</hi> We ſearch the Scriptures dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, and find that in Man that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves for Sin, is the Spirit of him that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſinned, ſee <hi>John</hi> 16.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 13, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here the Quakers ignorance and Blindneſs, (that the Presbyterian doth juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charge him withal) is manifeſt, that he is not taught according to Scripture, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt the ſeveral inward Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations and Operations of one and the ſame Spirit, and the ſeveral inward Lights and Illuminations, all coming from one and the ſame Author and Fountain, <hi>via.</hi> God, and Chriſt (conſidered as the divine Word)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:31315:4"/>and the Spirit, according to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4, 5, 6. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. and his Argument from <hi>John</hi> 16.7, 8, 9. &amp;c. Is a meer Perverſion, it being evident to all truly enlightened Chriſtians, that the Miſſion of the Spirit, the Comforter that Chriſt promiſed ſhould lead them into all Truth, to whom he ſhould be ſent, and who ſhould reprove the World for the Sin of not believing in Chriſt, to wit, Chriſt Crucified, and ſhould teſtifie to them of Chriſt, as he ſuffered Death for our Sins, was not on the account of the common Illumination, given to all Men, which the Diſciples had before the Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was ſent in that ſpecial Miniſtration. And unleſs he had proved that all Men are reproved by the common Illumination, for their not believing in Chriſt Crucified, and raiſed again, which he hath not ſo much as attempted, his Argument is Vain and Impertinent. And as Impertinent is he in his Arguing from other Places of Scripture; for let the Places be read and conſidered, and it will appear, they all point at ſome other and more excellent ſort and manner of Hlu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, than that common to all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, the Places are <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. <hi>James</hi> 1.21. For all theſe Places reſpect the State of Believers in Chriſt Crucified, and the peculiar Goſpel Diſpenſation, as diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31315:5"/>from that of Heathens and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, who are ſaid to be without.</p>
            <p>P. 7. He brings in the Presbyterian, not truly ſtating the Controverſie; but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts his oppoſite words, in this his Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, in way of anſwer to that called, <hi>a ſober Dialogue between a Country Friend, a London Friend, and one of</hi> G. K.<hi>'s Friends;</hi> for whereas the words in that Dialogue were, that what <hi>ſimply</hi> condemns us for Sin, does not forgive us; this unfair Quaker leaves out the word <hi>ſimply,</hi> which was main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary, truly to ſtate the Controverſie, <hi>viz.</hi> whither that Principle within Men, that only reproves or condemns them for Sin, and but convinceth of ſome moral du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and doth not propoſe to them <hi>that great Object</hi> of Faith, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> as he ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Death on the Croſs, for the remiſſion of our Sins, doth ſave them, without Chriſt Crucified, and without all Faith in him, as ſuch, the word <hi>ſimply</hi> having the ſame ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication with the word only.</p>
            <p>Pag. 8. He excuſeth <hi>G. Whitehead</hi>'s cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>G. K.</hi> who never curſed any of them, but prays for them, that he and <hi>G. W.</hi> are not apt to revile and curſe: This is like a Man, that being often Drunk, ſaith he is not apt to be Drunk; but why then hath <hi>G. W.</hi> done it; his too great aptneſs to curſe and revile is too apparent by ſad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31315:5"/>yea he hath not only curſed <hi>G. K.</hi> but joyned with ſome of his Brethren to damn the Three Perſons of the ever Holy and Bleſſed Trinity to the Pit, witneſs his and their Book in Anſwer to <hi>Townſend</hi>'s, Signed by him, and others, called, <hi>Iſmael,</hi> &amp;c. his late Excuſe of its being either wrong Writ, or wrong Printed, (without a plain Retractation) is inſufficient; Writ about forty Years after the former, in that called the <hi>Quakers Cleared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 9. He blames his Opponent, for ſaying, that <hi>Cornelius</hi> was not to be ſaved by the <hi>Light within,</hi> without ſomething elſe, but gives no Anſwer to the Argument brought by his Opponent in the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Dialogue, p. 9. How that an Angel muſt be ſent to him to tell him, that he muſt ſend for <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> which was to tell him words, by which he muſt be ſaved, and theſe words were to teach him, that he was to be ſaved, not <hi>ſimply,</hi> or only by the <hi>Light,</hi> or Chriſt within him, without Chriſt that was outwardly Crucified, and Faith in him.</p>
            <p>Page 9. He proceeds in his falſe Way of Stating the Controverſie, and Arguing from a falſe Hypotheſis, that becauſe that <hi>Light</hi> in all Men is God, and God is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and able to ſave all. For the true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie is not, what God can do, but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31315:6"/>what Sufficiency of Help he hath given to all Men for their eternal Salvation; as whether this Help is only and alone the <hi>Light within,</hi> as it ſignifies the common Illumination, or as it ſignifies the <hi>Divine Word,</hi> as giving to Men, only an inward Illumination, diſcovering God's eternal Power, and ſome moral Principles of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety and Juſtice, and general Piety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, conſidered only as a Creator, without Chriſt Crucified, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſpecial Revelation of God concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt, as he was Crucified, died for our Sins, roſe and Aſcended. This is the true State of the Queſtion, and by the whole Tenor of this Quakers Diſcourſe, he fully agrees with his meer Deiſt Brethren, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly <hi>G. W.</hi> and <hi>W. P.</hi> That hold that the <hi>Light within every Man,</hi> is ſufficient to his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without any thing elſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> Chriſt Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, and without all Faith in him as ſuch.</p>
            <p>Page 10. Having Perverted, and Miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied ſeveral places of Scripture, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 4.21. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 60.5. &amp;c. [All which have a ſpecial Reference to Chriſt without us, as he is offered in the Doctrin of the Goſpel, together with the ſpecial In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations and Illuminations given to the Faithful, in the belief of the Goſpel] to prove that the <hi>Light within</hi> ſaveth without any thing elſe, he bringeth in his Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31315:6"/>to aſſent to, and approve of all this his groſs Perverſion, and Miſapplication of the Scriptures, and makes his Church-man aſſent to the Quakers Proof, which he calls his <hi>Principal Proof</hi> out of the Goſpel, to be Read on <hi>Chriſtmas Day,</hi> adding, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members they, (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Church of <hi>England</hi>) Pray that <hi>God would inſpire them with his holy Spirit, that they may always think and do thoſe things which pleaſe him,</hi> whence he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, and then we muſt needs have this within us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What a Fictitious and Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, as well as Ignorant Church-man the Quaker here introduceth; as if the Church of <hi>England</hi> by this Prayer, Prayed only to be ſaved by the common Illumination, and did not Pray for ſpecial ſuperadded Illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and Inſpirations, above, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the common.</p>
            <p>But whereas he fains the Author of the fore-mentioned Dialogue to be a <hi>Scotch</hi> Presbyterian, the Quakers infallible Diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hath here failed him; for that Author is neither Presbyterian, nor <hi>Scotch-man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 13. The Quaker ſaith, they faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully believe all thoſe things, and all other holy Doctrins contained in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>viz.</hi> That Chriſt has bought us with his moſt precious Blood, the Reſurrection
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:31315:7"/>of that holy Body, with it's Aſcenſion into Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But how do they believe them? in a quite other Senſe, than is either meant in Scripture, or underſtood by all ſound Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
            <p>Page 15. The Quaker ſaith, yea, that Spirit which he promiſed ſhould bring all things to our Remembrance, we have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and it brings to our Remembrance God's great love in ſending his Son, and Chriſt's great Love in Suffering and Dying for us, and bows our Spirits, and tenders our Hearts in the living Remembrance of him, and inables us in true Humility to bleſs God, and gave thanks to him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> How this ſeeming Confeſſion doth conſiſt with his and his Brethrens ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the <hi>Light</hi> within them, and in every Man, is ſufficient to Salvation, without any thing elſe, I leave to Impartial and Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Readers to Judge; as alſo how it is conſiſtent with <hi>G. W.</hi>'s ſaying, its contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. To ſay, we are to believe in a Chriſt, whoſe Perſon is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended into Heaven above the Clouds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us, and that a <hi>Perſonal Being of</hi> Chriſt in Heaven without us, is <hi>Muggletoniſm</hi> and <hi>Anthropomorphitiſme.</hi> And laſtly, how is this Confeſſion conſiſtent with the Words of <hi>J. W.</hi> one of their Brethren, in his Book,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:31315:7"/>call'd, <hi>the Doctrin of Perfection Vindicated,</hi> by <hi>J. W.</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Wilſon,</hi> 1663. p. 18.</p>
            <p>Page 18. <q rend="inline">Therefore all came down to that of God, made manifeſt in you, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it with a willing Mind, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 19. For it is ſaid to be a Schoolmaſter to bring you to Chriſt, the Light and Lamb of God, who takes away Sin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Even by ſlaying it upon the Croſs, which is the Power of God which overcomes, or rather comes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and ſo brings under the Power of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So when you come to know this, you will ceaſe remembring his Death at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and will come to ſee how he hath been Crucified in you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Their common Anſwer, that Chriſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be divided, uſed by the Quaker in this Dialogue in ſeveral places, is evidently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; for why then do they make the <hi>Light</hi> within every Man ſufficient to Salvation, without the Manhood of Chriſt without them? but though Chriſt without, and Chriſt within, cannot be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, as neither his Godhead from his Manhood, nor his Spirit from his Body, yet they are diſtinguiſhed, and the Spirit is not the Body, nor is the Body and Manhood of Chriſt in Believers, though ſome of them ſay they have whole Chriſt in them, God, and Man, Fleſh, and Spirit, as <hi>G. F.</hi> hath affirmed in his <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> and <hi>W. Penn</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:31315:8"/>hath juſtified him in his ſo ſaying; that becauſe they eat his Fleſh, therefore it is in them vainly and ignorantly arguing from a Metaphorical Eating, to a literal and carnal Eating.</p>
            <p>Page 20. His Evaſion, as to the ſaying of ſome of them, that they are not unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Servants, becauſe they acknowledge they are not able to do any thing that good is without Chriſt, is fallacious, and reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not to the Senſe of Chriſt's Words, <hi>When ye have done all that ye ought to do, ſay, ye are unprofitable Servants,</hi> which compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends all that holy Men can or ought to do, even by the help of Chriſt, without whom, they neither can, nor ought to do any good.</p>
            <p>Page the ſame, He pretends to own, that great is the Myſtery of Godlineſs, God was manifeſt in the Fleſh, in this he is Fallaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, if he be of one Mind with <hi>W. P.</hi> who hath ſaid in Print, that the Work of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration is much more a Myſtery, than God manifeſt in the Fleſh.</p>
            <p>Page 21. He gives no plain Anſwer to that Query, whether muſt all our Spirits go when we die, muſt all go into the Quakers for Reſt and Peace. But Retorts the Queſtion from the Apoſtles, ſaying, that Chriſt within, was the Hope of Glory. What! (ſaith he) muſt all go into the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Primitive Chriſtians for Reſt and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31315:8"/>Peace? But this is an idle Retorſion, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Paul,</hi> or any of the Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ever ſaid that Chriſt, only within was their Hope of Glory, nor ever blamed the Doctrin of a local Heaven and Hell without Men; as ſome of your chief Men have done, particularly <hi>W. P.</hi> calling it Mahumetan, and both <hi>G. W.</hi> and <hi>W. P.</hi> have Printed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the deceaſed Saints, expecting any fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Reſurrection of the Body, arguing, that it would follow, they were in a State of Purgatory at the preſent time.</p>
            <p>Page 21. In his ſeeming to magnifie the Scriptures, which he ſaith, they are willing to take for the Confeſſion of their Faith, [which yet that they do not, is evident, otherwiſe they could not be guilty of ſuch groſs Errors] he brings them down to a Level with their own Writing, if not rather below them; for this he ſaith, and we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem them better than any Man, or Men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did, or can make, that have not the Guidance of that Spirit the holy Men were guided by. For ſeeing they believe they are infallibly Guided by the ſame holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, it is a plain Inſinuation, the Quakers Writings being given forth by the Guidance of the ſame holy Spirit, are at leaſt as good, if not better, and if this be not the plain Conſequence of his Words, I leave the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Reader to Judge, together with the reſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:31315:9"/>
            <head>Some further Anſwer by another Hand, with ſome Words of tender Exhortation Advice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS for the real Quaker, I have ſomewhat to offer to him, ſince he calls himſelf a real Quaker, I would fain know what a Quaker ſignifies, and whether it be a better or more proper Name than a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; beſides, I think the Quaker is decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in giving himſelf that Name, believing that never any of them had thoſe dreadful Sights as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Habakkuk,</hi> and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul.</hi> Pray, which of them ever heard the Voice of God ſpeaking to them with their outward Ears, or have heard or ſeen the Lords Chriſt without them; but they ſay they have heard his Voice inwardly, and ſeen his Shape inwardly; ſo have thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands that never call'd themſelves by that Name, and they pretend to no other Light, than what enlightens every Man that comes into the World, and ſince it is ſo univerſal, that every Man has it, why is the Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thought ſo aſtoniſhing to them, as to cauſe ſuch Horror and Trembling to them above all Mankind beſides. Surely the Quaker would make us believe hereby that the Light in every Man metes with greater Oppoſition in them, becauſe of their many and great Sins, than it metes with in many other Men; I have often known that ſome
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31315:9"/>which have been reproved by that Light, have greatly rejoiced, believing it to be a Sign, that their Conſciences are yet alive, and not made Shipwrack of; ſo that by the Name they give themſelves, we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them to be the greateſt of Sinners; otherwiſe why ſhould ſuch Horror attend them, more than all the World beſides. One would think they were very dark to be thus amazed at the ſight of that Light that is ſo common to every Man in the World, and to rejoyce in the Name of a Quaker, more than in the Name of a Child of Light, that being firſt given to them, but they ſlighted that Name, and choſe rather the Name of a Quaker, which no true Child of Light would ever have done, becauſe that Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling is a Diſpenſation of Terror and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, which is ſaid to attend the Night, but Joy comes in the Morning, and you tell all the World that there is no better nor high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er a State than that of the Quaker; pray what are thoſe great Attainments you have arrived at beyond other People; it may be you will ſay you have left the Faſhions and Language of the World, well, and what then? Will all this quiet a Conſcience wounded with Sin? I tell you nay, Sheeps Cloathing will not do, when you will not hear the voice of the true Shepherd, nor fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his Commandments. We Read of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:31315:10"/>but one Shepherd, and one Sheep-fold, which was that good Shepherd that laid down his Life for his Sheep. And in your Dialogue, you tell us, that the Light in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man is the divine Word, which you call Chriſt; 'tis true, Chriſt was that divine Word in the beginning with God, and here you make a full ſtop, and tell us that that does enlighten every Man that comes into the World, and Calls, Exhorts, and ſtrives with every Man, in order to ſave them, which if received, works the Salvation of all. Now, if the <hi>Divine Word,</hi> as it was in the beginning, ſaves all Mankind; pray what was remaining for that <hi>Word</hi> to do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it was made <hi>Fleſh;</hi> did not all the holy Men of old know that <hi>Divine Word,</hi> and its Operation, far beyond the beſt of you? And yet how did they rejoyce, that by Faith they ſaw Chriſts Day in the Fleſh, they clearly ſaw that great Myſtery of Godlineſs, Chriſt manifeſt in the Fleſh; and does not St. <hi>John</hi> begin with the Creation, and tells us that in the beginning was the Word, and how that Word did Operate in being the Light of Men, and ſo goes down to <hi>John</hi> the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, and from him to the Birth of Chriſt; ſaying in the <hi>14th verſe, that that</hi> Divine Word <hi>was made fleſh, and dwelt among them,</hi> and ſaith he, <hi>we beheld his glory, the glory as of the only begotten of the Father, full of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:31315:10"/>grace and truth.</hi> And pray was not old <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon,</hi> well acquainted with that <hi>Divine Word,</hi> which was the Light of Men; yet when he ſaw the Child Jeſus, he ſaid, now let thy Servant depart in Peace, for my Eyes have ſeen thy Salvation, a Light to Lighten the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and the Glory of thy People <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And another Propheteſs gave a full Teſtimony to all that looked, for Redemption in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Now, here is that <hi>Divine Word,</hi> which under the Law did ſhew Man his Sin, and under the Goſpel ſaves him from Sin; pray, which of thoſe two was the moſt glorious Manifeſtation to Mankind, as to that Prophecy in <hi>John</hi> the 16th. <hi>verſe</hi> the 7.8, 9, 10, 11, 13. Pray conſider to whom our Lord ſpeaks; was it not to his afflicted Diſciples, whom he was juſt a going to leave in a dark and wicked World, and therefore told them that he would ſend that Comforter, the Spirit of Truth, which would guide them into all Truth. [Mind] he was a Guide to the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, but a Reprover to the World of Sin, becauſe they believed not in Chriſt Jeſus, and ſaith our Lord in the 14th <hi>verſe, He ſhall glorifie me, for he ſhall receive of mine, and ſhall ſhew it unto you; for he ſhall not ſpeak of himſelf, but what ſoever he ſhall hear, that ſhall he ſpeak.</hi> Here you ſee, and as you deſired ſome places of Scripture, that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:31315:11"/>the holy Ghoſt, or Comforter, does not ſave without Chriſt Jeſus, neither is the Holy Ghoſt ſaid to be the Chriſt, but he did take of Chriſt, and was a Meſſenger from Chriſt, to Comfort his ſuffering Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in his abſence, and to confirm that Doctrin. And did you ever read that any did receive the Holy Ghoſt, that did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt Jeſus, as he outwardly came in the Fleſh. And where is the Man that can ſay among any of the Quakers, that he has received the Holy Ghoſt, as it was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the Apoſtles Days; notwithſtanding the real Quaker ſaith that every Man has it, and ſaith, that with all the Presbyterians Logick, and the outward Knowledge of Chriſt, or of what he hath ſuffered out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly for us, he cannot ſtop the Cries of that which Reproves for Sin. I believe no true Chriſtian deſires to ſtop its cry againſt Sin; but methinks the Man ſhould have been more ſerious, then to put Logick, and the outward Knowledge of what Chriſt did, and ſuffered together. I fear the real Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker eſteems them too much alike; he ſays further, that with all thy Art and Skill, thou canſt not prove that <hi>Water Baptiſme</hi> was commanded by Chriſt, 'tis a ſtrange ſaying, and vain enough.</p>
            <p>But pray what thinks he of the 3d of St. <hi>John,</hi> the 26th <hi>verſe,</hi> What were all they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:31315:11"/>Baptized with that came to Chriſt? That 'tis ſaid that Jeſus Baptized not, but his Diſciples did, and how ſhould they Baptize with the Holy Ghoſt, when Chriſt was not yet gone from them, and therefore had not yet ſeen the Holy Ghoſt; and did not <hi>Peter,</hi> on his relating of the Holy Ghoſt's falling on <hi>Cornelius</hi>'s Family ſay, that then he remembred the Words of the Lord, how they ſhould be Baptized with the Holy Ghoſt, and yet he Adminiſtred Water after, and can any Man be ſo Ignorant, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the Holy Apoſtles of our Lord would have Baptized with Water, had they not known that it was their Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's Will and Commandment, whatever others may doe without Commiſſion, they were too Holy, and too Spiritual to do ſuch things. He ſpeaks after the like manner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Lord's Supper, and then Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects on <hi>G. K.</hi> what he Wrote when he was one of them, I would to God they were as honeſt to acknowledge their being miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; as he has done both by Word and Writing, and in that thing they do but the more expoſe themſelves, ſince they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver found fault with him, till they ſaw him further enlightened. It is ſaid that Jeſus did not commit himſelf to all Men, becauſe he knew what was in Man; how then is he
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:31315:12"/>in every Man, a ſufficient Saviour only by that common Illumination?</p>
            <p>And now I have a few Words to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and ſober Quakers: My Friends, I do beſeech you to ſearch the Holy Scriptures, and believe they were Written for our Learning, for our Conviction, for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, that the Man of God may be furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to every good Work, notwithſtanding your Teachers bids you only to mind, that in your own Hearts, I do tell you that to bring your own Deeds to the Light, is to bring them to the Doctrin of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, as God ſhall be pleaſed ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to enlighten you to underſtand it; why ſhould you lean to your own Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, when the great God has made ſuch wonderful Proviſion for you, and has ſet it on a Candleſtick, for all Men to ſee the Light thereof in our Land, tho' not ſo in all Lands. Pray what a Price did both the Old and New Teſtament coſt them that conveyed it to us; did it not come ſwiming to us in a River of Blood, and ſhall we ſo ill requite the great God, and thoſe dear Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and Meſſengers, as to tell we have no need of their Teſtimonies or Doctrin; for every Man has that in himſelf that will ſave him, if he hearkens to it's Voice. What Ingratitude is this to thoſe holy Martyrs,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:31315:12"/>whoſe Blood cries, how long e'er thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge us on them that dwell on the Earth.</p>
            <p>And where do you find that God ever left any of his choſen ones to the common Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of Light, only in themſelves, that being too much vailed by the Fall of Man, had Man been left to that Witneſs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out higher Manifeſtations to excite Faith and Hope of Redemption, by an Object be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yong themſelves; how had they fainted in their Minds, and conſidering how their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Adam</hi> had fallen before them who doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs had more Light than any earthly Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſince he was in the Paradice of God. I muſt needs ſay I am concerned for you, and it makes me even tremble to ſee on what a brink of danger you ſtand; there are too many Children that can ſpeak be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they go, which is no good Sign; I fear you have not tried your own Frailty, that talk thus big. I am ſure that there are ſome among you that has as much need to pray for the Forgiveneſs of Sin, as any Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the World has, and yet at the ſame time will ſay that they have that in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that is able to ſave them from all Sin; they may as well ſay they have a Staff in their Hands, but will not make uſe of it, ſo do nothing but ſtumble and fall; will not all the World condemn you, and ſay, ſince theſe Men have ſo great a Light, as is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:31315:13"/>to ſave them, why do they not follow it, but fall into ſuch horrid Miſtakes in their way. I do really believe, whenever God o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens the Eyes of your Teachers, which have cauſed you to err, to ſee what they have done, and what they are doing, they will then deſerve the Name of Quaker, more than ever they did? I pray God open their Eyes, for your and their own ſakes, that they may have their Suffering rather in this Life, then in that which is to come. Do not miſtake me, and think that I deſign to leſſen the <hi>Light</hi> that in Man that Reproves for Sin, or the Law Written in the Heart: as the Apoſtle plainly calls it, and ſaid he had not known Sin, but by the Law, but Chriſt's Blood is the Way by which we muſt enter in. Therefore do not think of climbing up another way. I do intreat you, my Friends to read the Scriptures, eſpecially the New Teſtament, through and through again, and pray to the Lord for Wiſdom in the Reading of them, and they will ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently furniſh you with Wiſdom, that is able to make you wiſe to Salvation, through Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, and know withal that theſe Lines are Written from one that is your real and hearty Friend, that Prays for your Salvation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:31315:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
